BLS Wage and Earnings Reports 5392
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
BLS Wage and Earnings Reports
1909-1952
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS)
5392
3.5 cubic feet
3.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Results of studies and surveys on wages, earnings, and productivity trends.
5622649
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 16, 2005
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The need for the collection of labor statistics was recognized by Congress in 1884 when it established the Bureau of Labor in the Department of the Interior. In 1913 the Bureau was transferred to the newly created Department of Labor under the title Bureau of Labor Statistics.
The Commissioner is nominated by the President of the United States. He has advisory committees from labor and management to provide him with practical advice in the preparation and publication of statistics that will be most useful.
The Bureau's work is divided into eight main divisions and currently goes far beyond the collection of labor statistics. There are five regional offices which collect information within their geographical area.
Productivity statistics are the responsibility of the Productivity and Technological Development Section of the Manpower and Productivity Division.
Productivity studies began with the creation of the Bureau when unemployment raised questions about the replacement of men by machines. In 1898 a study was made on the labor input required according to the manufacturing process adapted. In 1925 labor organizations urged the Bureau to determine the progress of technical developments for they felt labor was not getting its fair share.
With the depression, interest was focussed on unemployment and the American Federation of Labor was responsible for a continuing study of productivity and labor costs under the Works Progress Administration.
At the end of World War II productivity in relation to wages became an important factor in the negotiation of labor contracts, but the measurement of productivity was subject to considerable disagreement. The Bureau of the Budget and the Bureau of Labor Statistics called a conference of experts to help bring the methods of calculating productivity up to date. The Congress voted additional funds for a new approach to the problem.
Beginning in 1946 the Bureau began studies of productivity based on data provided voluntarily by a group of sample firms as well as on calculations from other statistical sources. The results of both series were published and widely-circulated and a short summary published in the Monthly Labor Review. The studies include a great deal of background information on the industry and are written for all potential users.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5403 mf: U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics Budget for Special Reports on Microfilm 6178: BLS/OLMS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements
Cost and standard of living -- United States; Wages -- United States; United States. Bureau of Labor Statistics
5622649
- Agriculture, 1909-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agriculture, 1909-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- the Anthracite Mining Industry, 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- the Bituminous Coal Mining Industry, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- the Bituminous Coal Mining Industry, 1935-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- the Bread and other Bakery Products Industry (Box 1, Folder 6)
- the Canning and Preserving Industries, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- the Cement Industry, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- the Clay Construction Products Industries, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- the Clay Construction Products Industries, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- the Coke Oven Industries, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- the Condensed and Evaporated Milk Industry, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- the Confectionery Industry, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- the Copper Ores Mining Industry, 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Dome Reflectors, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Scope and Contents
  Mar-52
- Electric Light and Power Industry, 1917-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Capital Requirements and Operating Ratios in the Electric Motor Industry (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Standardization, Simplification, Specialization in Electrically Operated Household Appliances, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Nov-52
- the Fluorescent Lighting Fixtures, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Jan-52
- the Flour and Other Grain Mill Products Industry, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- the Footwear (Except Rubber) Industry, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- the Glass Containers Industry, 1939-1951 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- the Hosiery Industries, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- the Ice Cream Industry, 1919-1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- the Gray Iron Foundries, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Aug-51
- the Iron Mining Industry, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Power Laundries, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  December 1951
- Lead and Zinc Ores Mining Industries, 1935-1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- the Leather Industry, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- the Malt Liquors Industry, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Men's Bib Overalls and Men's Work Jackets, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Men's Dress Shirts, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Men's Dress Shoes, Goodyear Welt, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Capital Requirements and Operating Ratios - Men's Shirt Industry, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Men's Work Clothing, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Men's Work Pants, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Dec-51
- Supplement to Men's Work Pants: List of Machinery Used (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Mens Work Shirts, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Nov-51
- Men's Work Shirts, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Pulp and Paper Mills, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Radio and Television Manufacturing (Box 1, Folder 41)
- the Railroad Transportation Industry, 1935-1951 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Rayon and Other Synthetic Fibers Industry, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- School Bus Bodies, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Feb-52
- Primary Smelting and Refining of Copper, Lead, and Zinc, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Primary Smelting and Refining of Copper, Lead, and Zinc, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Street Lighting Luminaires, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Street Lighting Luminaires (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Telephone and Telegraph Industries, 1935-1947 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Tobacco Products Industries, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Tobacco Products Group, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Women's Dress Shoes, Cement Process, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Selected Types of Construction Machinery, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Selected Types of Construction Machinery, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Selected Types of Construction Machinery, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Selected Types of Construction and Mining Machinery, Supplement, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Electrical Equipment and Supplies, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Household Electrical Appliances, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Household Electrical Appliances, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Household Electrical Appliances, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Household Electrical Appliances, Supplement, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Selected Types of Fertilizer, 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Selected Types of Fertilizer, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Selected Types of Fertilizer, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Fertilizer, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Fertilizer, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Footwear, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Footwear, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Footwear, Supplement, 1939-1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Hours and Earnings - Industry Report (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Selected Types of Industrial Equipment, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Selected Types of Industrial Equipment, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- General Industrial Equipment, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Selected types of General Industrial Equipment, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Selected types of General Industrial Equipment, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Supplement
- Unit Man-Hour Requirements in Selected Industries, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Selected types of Leather, 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Selected types of Leather, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Selected Types of Leather, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Selected Types of Leather, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Selected Types of Luggage, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Selected Machine Tools, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Selected types of Machine Tools, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Selected types of Machine Tools, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Selected types of Machine Tools, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Selected types of Machine Tools, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Men's Dress Shirts, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Men's Dress Shirts, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Men's Dress and Sport Shirts, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Man Hours, Men's Dress and Short Shirts, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Men's Work Clothing, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Selected Metal Forming Machinery, 1939-1949 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Mining, 1935-1949 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Selected Types of Mining Machinery, 1939-1949 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Home Radio Receivers, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Radio and Television Manufacturing Supplement, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Man-Hours Expended per Car - Selected Types of Railroad Freight Cars, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Soap and Glycerin Manufacture, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Soap and Glycerin Manufacture, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Soap and Glycerin Manufacture, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Cane Sugar Refining, 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Cane Sugar Refining, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Cane Sugar Refining, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Cain Sugar Refining, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Synthetic Rubber and Components, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Television and Radio BetB, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Radio, Television and related Products (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Office Building Service, Occupational Earnings (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Sheet Metal Work (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Sawmills + Planing Mills (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Sawmills (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Sawmilling - West Coast (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Rubber Products (Except Tires, Etc.) (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Rayon, Nylon + Silk Textiles (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Special Dies + Tools, Die Sets, Jigs (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Railroad Cars (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Stamped + Pressed Metal Products (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Pulp, Paper and paperboard (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Pressed + Blown Glassware (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Power Laundries + Dry Cleaning (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Power Laundries (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Pottery and Related Products (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Petroleum Refining (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Paper + Paperboard Mills, Occupational Earnings (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Paints and Barnishes, Occupational Earnings (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Raw Sugar (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Women's + Misses Coats and Suits (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Union Wage Scales - Printing Trades (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Union Wage Scales, Building Trades Union Wage Scales - Local Transit Operating Employees (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Straight-Time Hourly Earnings Work Clothing (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Woolen + Worsted Textiles (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Wood Furniture-other than upholstered (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Women's Cement Pro. Shoes (Slip Lasted) (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Women's Cement PTO Shoes (Con. Lasted) (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Southern Sawmills (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Women's + Misses Dresses (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Union Wage Scales - Motor Trucking Drivers + Helpers Trade (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Tobacco Stemming + Redrying (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Tin Cans and Other Tinware (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Textile Dyeing and Finishing Synthetic, Broad Woven Fabrics (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Textile Dyeing and Finishing Cotton Broad Woolen Fabrics (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Textile Dyeing and Finishing (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Synthetic Textiles (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Structural Clay Products (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Steel Foundries (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Women's Cement Processed Shoes (Box 3, Folder 32)